Guide to the Erik Bert Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Erik Bert Papers
1924-1980.
Bert, Erik.
7 linear ft (ca.1000 items in l6 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078392
This collection contains the personal and professional papers of Marxist scholar and editor Herbert Joseph Putz written under the pseudonym Erik Bert.
Biographical Note
Erik Bert was the pseudonym of Herbert Joseph Putz, -1981, (Columbia B.A., 1926, M.A., 1927), Marxist scholar and editor of "The Producers News" and the "Farmers National Weekly" for 40 years. He served on the editorial board of "The Daily Worker" and "The Daily World." He contributed many articles to "Political Affairs," the theoretical journal of the U.S. Communist Party, on agrarian reform, communism and Communist Party conferences, Czechoslovakia in 1968, civil rights, capitalism, and on other economic subjects.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts of book reviews and essays, conference notes and reports, book manuscripts, copy editing for other authors, notebooks, press releases, photographs, clippings and other printed materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Subject File
Series II: Notebooks
Subjects
Communist Party of America.; Agriculture and politics.; Communism.; Photoprints; Journalists
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1983 Papers Putz, Ruth Gift
Gift of Mrs. Ruth Putz, 1983.
Related Material
Bert's agricultural manuscripts were given to the University of Iowa Libraries, Iowa City, Iowa.
- Series I: Subject File
  - Agricultural Census of 1969 (Box 1)
  - Agricultural Production in Postwar America (Box 1)
  - Anthology (notes) (Box 1)
  - The Automobile Business (master's thesis) (Box 1)
  - Baron, Paul A. 5 The Political Economy of Growth (bk rev) (Box 1)
  - Benson, Ezra Taft; Freedom to Farm (bk rev) (Box 1)
  - Bert, Erik (misc.) (Box 1)
  - Bert, Erik; "Veblin and Marx" (bk rev) (Box 1)
  - Bert, Erik; "Vulgar Economy" (Box 1)
  - Berthold, Lothar; (misc.) (Box 1)
  - Brecht, Bertolt; Berlin (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Browder, Earl; Marx and America (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Burns, Arthur F.; The Business Cycle in a Changing World (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Carrillo, Santiago; "Eurocommunism" and the State (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights Commission, U.S. (Box 2)
  - Clark, B.H.5 The Tennessee Yeomen (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Clawson, Marion; Policy Directions for U.S., Agriculture (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Columbia Papers by Bert (Box 2)
  - Commons, John R. 5 Monopoly Capitalism II (bk rev) (Box 2)
  - Communist International (Pragues January, 1978) (Box 3)
  - Communist Party Draft Number Two (Box 3)
  - Communist Party Draft Program, (4 Folders) (Box 3)
  - Communist Party Draft Resolution (1975) (Box 3)
  - Communist Party Farm Program (Box 4)
  - Communist Party Poverty Program (Box 4)
  - Communist Party, USA (Box 4)
  - Corruption in Government (Box 4)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - General Material (Box 4)
    - Articles by Bert (Box 4)
    - Black Books (Box 4)
    - Central Control and Auditing Commission (Box 4)
    - Communist Party (Box 4)
    - Communist Party's Fourteenth Congress, (2 Folders) (Box 4)
    - Communist Party:"Lessons" (Box 5)
    - Communist Party:Party Lecture (Box 5)
    - Communist Party:Resolutions and Statements (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Huzak (Box 5)
    - L' Humanite (Box 5)
    - Manuscripts and Notes (Box 5)
    - Manuscripts by Others (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Neues Deutschland (Box 6)
    - 1968 (Box 6)
    - Press Clippings, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
    - Press Releases (Czech Embassy) (Box 6)
    - Press Releases (Miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Press Releases (Novosti) (Box 6)
    - Press Releases (Pragopress) (Box 6)
    - Press Releases (Rude Pravo) (Box 7)
    - Press Releases (Tass) (Box 7)
    - Press Releases (UPI) (Box 7)
    - Since the Prague Spring (Box 7)
    - Strougal and Lubomir (Box 7)
  - Dialogue as Quid Pro Quo (Box 7)
  - Diskin, Louis (letter) (Box 7)
  - Dowd, Douglas; Thorstein Veblin (bk rev) (Box 7)
  - Draft Main Political Solution (Box 7)
  - Dyson, Lowell K.; (letter) (Box 7)
  - Eurocommunism and Detente, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - Eurocommunism (manuscripts I - III) (Box 7)
  - Eurocommunism (manuscripts IV and V) (Box 8)
  - Fabricant (Box 8)
  - Falling Rate of Profit (Box 8)
  - Foster; History of the CPUSA (notes) (Box 8)
  - Galbraith, John K.; Economics and the Public Purpose (bk rev) (Box 8)
  - Galbraith; The New Industrial State (bk rev) (Box 8)
  - GDR Speech (June, 1980) (Box 8)
  - Global Reach (Box 8)
  - Gollwitzer, Helmut-(notes) (Box 8)
  - Gronlunds, Laurence; The Cooperative Commonwealth (bk rev) (Box 8)
  - Hall, Gus (Political Reports and Correspondences) (Box 9)
  - Harrington, Michael; Socialism (bk rev) (Box 9)
  - Harris, Lement (letter) (Box 9)
  - Ihde, Horst (letter) (Box 9)
  - "Herman Kriege, the California Democrats, and Marx and Engels" (report) (Box 9)
  - Kuznets, Simon; Economic Growth of Nations (bk rev), (2 Folders) (Box 9)
  - Labor and Agriculture (clippings from The Congressional Record) (Box 9)
  - "Lenin on the United States" (Box 9)
  - "Lessons" (Box 9)
  - Lochman, Jan M.; Church in a Marxist Society (bk rev), (3 Folders) (Box 9)
  - Loebl, Eugen; Humanomics (bk rev) (Box 9)
  - Marek, Franz; Philosophy of World Revolution (bk rev) (letter) (Box 10)
  - Marx, Karl (Box 10)
  - Marx, Karl; Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy (centennial report) (Box 10)
  - Marx- Engels; Collected Works, vol, Z and 7 (2 Folders) (Box 10)
  - Mergers (notes by Bert) (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Myerson comment by Bert (Box 10)
  - Neo-Colonialism (Box 10)
  - "Nixon, Revisionism, and the Communist Manifesto" (Box 10)
  - Noyes, C.R.; A New Theory of Profits (bk rev) (Box 10)
  - "The Panic of 1857" (academic thesis?) (Box 11)
  - Plantation (report), (2 Folders) (Box 11)
  - Ponomarev Pamphlet (review and correspondences) (Box 11)
  - "The Political Bankruptcy of Maoism" (Box 11)
  - Prague Seminar (CPUSA contribution by Bert) (Box 11)
  - Putz, Nancy (playbills) (Box 11)
  - Putz, Ruth (letters) (Box 11)
  - Revisionism (Box 11)
  - "The Road to Transcendental Marxism" (Box 11)
  - Rochester, Anna; Lenin on the Agrarian Question (bk rev) (Box 11)
  - Sakharov-Salisbury (bk revs) (Box 11)
  - Schultz, T.W.; Transforming Traditional Agriculture (bk rev) (Box 11)
  - Segre, Sergio (interview notes) (Box 11)
  - Shover, Lement (letter) (Box 11)
  - "60th Anniversary of the October Revolution" (Box 11)
  - Soth, Lauren; Farm Troubles (bk rev) (Box 11)
  - "State Monopoly, Capitalism, .and Agriculture" (Box 12)
  - Transportation (2 Folders) (Box 12)
  - "Trotsky" (Box 12)
  - Veblin, T.; The Place of Science in Modern Civilization (bk (Box 12)
  - "The Web of Financial Capital" (Box 12)
  - Wechsberg, Joseph; The Voices (bk rev) (Box 12)
  - Wheeler, G.S.; The Human Face of Socialism (bk rev) (Box 12)
  - World Marxist Review Conference (1978 address) (Box 12)
  - Yugoslavia (report of visit to) (Box 12)
- Series II: Notebooks
  - Notebooks 1 - 13 (Box 13)
  - Notebooks 14 - 23 (Box 14)
  - Notebooks (un-numbered) (Box 15)
  - Stenography-type notebooks (Box 16)